[SPEAKER_01]: So, in regards to background and foreground mindfulness development, how should one regard the Self, so as to experience anatta, not Self?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the first thing is, one has to start seeing oneself.
[SPEAKER_00]: As something that's present there in that experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's because people don't develop mindfulness according to the principle of simultaneous presence of the background and the foreground, as in attention and that which is not attended, but simultaneously there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they usually can't see the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the self would be described as an elusive, ambiguous thing that you can never pin, pin it down, because you can't attend.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your sense of self, because that sense of self, it's always in the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sense of self kind of merges with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because background's always there, and sense of self, it's seemingly always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they share these characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, that results then in, in people just never seeing even, even as a phenomena, that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you start practicing mindfulness in terms of the discerning the peripheral phenomena without looking at them directly, you are discerning the domain where that sense of self does manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you get used to recognizing it for what it is and stop trying to attend to it directly and see it as an object of your senses or something, then you get to see that it's just there, a phenomena among other phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when that self becomes not-self, not-myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're saying it becomes... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, that thing, that self, it stays there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what changes is your attitude of ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you don't see it, you automatically own it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is your self.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you start seeing it, it ceases to be my self, which means ceases to be the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just becomes a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is a phenomenon as a background, unifying background of the experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by seeing self, where it is, how it is... By learning how to see the self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Learning how to see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you look at it, you won't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's behind your look.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why this peripheral mindfulness and vision results in knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the way of seeing it, so to speak, internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't see it just by moving your attention towards it, because it's not object of your senses or your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, trying to continuously or see self, know the self, one develops then anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta is developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: By properly
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting to know that sense of self, eh... one will be unable to maintain the notion of ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that automatically is the experience of another.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you see that the background is there to determine the foreground, inasmuch as foreground determines the background, there's absolutely no room for that self that you assume, self as the master, creator, owner of the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, normally, most people, we don't see the Self, we don't know the Self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, it sort of proliferates, expands and takes over our world, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, pretty much, yes, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is... whatever happens, it's mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the assumption of I am, I am the center of this experience, I am the center of the world, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no end to that, to proliferation of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, there is an end to that, if you remove the ownership of right things, then you won't be able to maintain that gratuitous assumption anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But until you do, you will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not a matter of volition to just stop willing things to be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what people sometimes resort to, like, when they're off.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ownership, having things as mine, is a problem, because it feeds my sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, they start destroying their ownership, their property, and throwing everything, giving everything to charity, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking that by getting rid of things you own, you get rid of your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that, that's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's throwing the, throwing the baby with the bathwater.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, getting rid of self-centeredness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, which is the ownership of your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have to give anything up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you have to give up sensuality, your will.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to give up a non-virtuous behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in terms of things you own, as like items and possessions, theoretically, you don't have to give anything up, if you give up the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can't own anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any ownership comes through the ownership of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why that's the... well, that's the problem, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to give the sense of self up, well, you need to see what that sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just give it up, theoretically, or wish to give it up, because you don't even know what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing it is giving it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nope.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you start discerning what it is, it becomes apparent that actually it has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impermanent in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are not the eternal master-creator of it, or controller, which means it's automatically then given up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, knowing the Self was being able to know the Self in the background, correctly, and
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's a phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nimitta is a phenomena as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nimitta is usually a sign in regard to the established phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, for most people, the sense of self appears on the level of the sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't even see it as a phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, they could develop their mind and start discerning the sense of self, as ambiguous as it is, real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: An ambiguous general peripheral phenomena present here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, they can start discerning nimitta in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because nimitta is not a fixed thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a designation for a position in a relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Signs and tokens do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you look at them, they're gonna have their own signs and tokens.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sign that comes
[SPEAKER_01]: The sign that comes from knowing the Self, or seeing the Self phenomenon, that sign is anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not automatically, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were told to look at it like that, then you will see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the external instruction is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if Pradyojana could become very authentic in this sense of Self and see it like a like a relatively
[SPEAKER_00]: dependent nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fundamentally, he will still remain assuming the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you just pointed out to actually see even that as any other phenomena, then you will start discerning the phenomena of the nimitta, as in the signs and tokens in regard to that phenomenon of self as actually not in my control, not mine, not pleasurable, dependent, thus not the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: These signs, those are like meanings.
Meanings?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the meaning of self?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, signs and token, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you didn't know it... That's what the sign is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a point in meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Points at something.
[SPEAKER_00]: A meaning of something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a, like a, a reference relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would be correct to say that the sign of the foreground
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sign is always in the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by looking at the background, you're going to start discerning the signs.
[SPEAKER_00]: By discerning the signs, you're becoming aware of the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by seeing the foreground, not going into it too much, not attending to the particulars too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, too much, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can attend to them if it won't compromise your mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if attending to the particulars of the foreground takes your mind away from the mindfulness of the experience as a whole, well, then you're compromising it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because being able to see the sign of the foreground, the background...
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be an established mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would that be the middle way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that is the middle way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the beginning of it.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you stick to that kind of mindfulness, you will develop, then, the discernment of the sign of, even further, which is the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the right view after that, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's the middle way, exactly because of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're neither giving in to the senses of the mind, nor you're mystifying and dismissing the whole thing going the other direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're kind of in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not from me here to there, or from there to me here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just these two things arise and cease simultaneously together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like nāmarūpa and viññāṇa, viññāṇa and nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all that's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not fully understanding that, you assume yourself in it, as the owner of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if one is in that state, state, I don't know how to use that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But go on, ask a question, then we can reformulate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If one is doing right mindfulness, balancing in the middle way, then when you act,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't act too... Too unwholesomely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Too unwholesomely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the right effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because greed, aversion, delusion is... it counters the balance, even in slightest amounts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somebody who is committed, discerning the practice of that balancing, as you said, then will just see that it's completely incompatible with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't practice the dhamma and engage in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you do, you fall from dhamma for that period of time, whatever you're engaging with, for however long you choose to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, you can you can call it balancing in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think of it like balancing you get used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you balance something for the sake of balancing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you, within the balance, you start discerning further opportunity for balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because somebody who has never ever stepped back and become aware of their own situation, doing that first time, would feel like, wow, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you get used to that, then you see, okay, well, now you can actually take the same principle even further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there is... there are subtler, more peripheral backgrounds to regard to your foreground, and there are more particular foregrounds with their own limiters and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same principle,
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you can take it further and further.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how far you take it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, as long as it takes until you're free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your measure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that perfect balance of non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion becomes like fully cemented form of being here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why when he studies himself in nibbāna, and the one who doesn't develop it fully, he falls from nibbāna, as the Buddha would describe in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like a great sort of, you know, I don't know, spiritual wave of energy that sweeps everything and just...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's diligence and repetition and hard work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha would always say, whatever was to be obtained by the manly effort, manly strength, manly commitment or whatever it was exactly he used, I have obtained.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't given to him by by luck or mystical experience or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He saw it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'd done it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He developed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Balance, maybe a better word is composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly, composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Balance, kind of, again, I mean, it's not, it's not a wrong term, but it's going to be misunderstood, no doubt about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you think about balance, think about composure, think about maintaining the sight of the background while not ignoring the foreground, or doing the... being engaged, attending to the foreground without losing the sight of the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's a form of balance that you... the more you do, the better you get at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jhāna is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Establishing your mind outside the domain of sensuality until it gets steadied in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sīla... sīla is the emulation of that balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't understand it, you don't know it, but you start emulating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which can then give rise to the actual understanding, because you have the setup in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're still not recognizing it,
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're emulating that, that can then, eventually, bring the recognition.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't recognize something, if there is... if that thing is not in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you recognize it as such and such, if it's not there altogether?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sīla and the virtue being the prerequisite to any practice of dharma, it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Emulating the right order, emulating the correct balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: The non-assumption, non-greed, non-aversion, non-self-centeredness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, that's why sīla in itself won't result in the dhamma, because you can emulate all you want, if you don't make the effort to understand and succeed in understanding what you're emulating, then you're not... then you haven't developed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's almost like training wheels, maybe, like keeping the rules with like training wheels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure, yeah, could be, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you can still be riding, you don't have to be...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like you... once you've understood
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma, the principle, you got the middle way, you're balancing there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't put... you let go of virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, exactly, because the purpose of the virtue is now your purpose of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the purpose of the training wheels was to keep you straight and flowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you're keeping straight and flowing without the training wheels.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yet, you've gone... you are straight and flowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've gone beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say, in a way, you go beyond, deep, beyond the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there were no precepts in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the Buddha would teach dhamma and that's exactly what people would understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: There wouldn't be many misunderstandings and wrong views about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those who understood it, they understood it right to the core.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, immediately, there was a reference point to anything that shouldn't be done from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that would be countering that balance or affecting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as the clarity that Balan started waning away, basically, it was sort of almost to the same extent, it was the increase in bad behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: But initially, like, there were no rules about, I don't know, eating, like, yeah, yeah, like not eating in the afternoon, for example, or eating once a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would eat, they would go pindapad at night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, some of the rules are risen in response to, like, interaction with society.
[SPEAKER_00]: It had nothing to do with dhamma or with obstructing the balance and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those that did arise on account of monks doing unwholesome things, that all came later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because initially, it was very clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is an obstacle to the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: And what isn't?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, something that isn't an obstacle can be a rule as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have many of the rules that are not actually obstacles.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the dhamma, it kind of arose and formulated in response to, like, as I said, interaction with people and societies and kings and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the ones that they were obstacle, yeah, they stayed obstacle.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: If something is an obstacle to the dhamma, it doesn't depend on the society and the social context that dhamma is practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It always relate to this universal principles of greed, aversion, delusion, being, obstruction to that balance, to that composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's when people try to argue.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I heard something as silly as that, that today you don't have to be celibate in order to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Back in the day, they needed to do that, because it was kind of dependent on the social context and everything else, so it's just plain ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: If anything, today you need to be twice as hard celibate than back then, because your sensuality is everywhere, completely accessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the minds are more proliferated and weaker than back then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people don't deal much with hardship today anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very few do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're not naturally tough.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, if anything, today you need to toughen up even more than back in the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if something is a direct obstacle, it's a universal obstacle, because dhamma is universal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't dismiss it because of a social context or requirement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, eating in the afternoon, wearing this type of robes or doing that, that's all, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing to do with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a way of expression, a way of relating to other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not a problem for that very reason either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you have that basic, or that understanding of balancing, or the middle way... Or practice of mindfulness and composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were saying about diligence, you know, just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Not giving in to unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, well, we spoke the other day, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the thing, you... By practicing mindfulness correctly, by being properly composed, the issues of greed, aversion, delusion become clearer.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you know exactly the extent of your responsibility in those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means then you know exactly, or gradually, you increase the accuracy of your recognition of what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you're not saying no to everything and everyone all the time, because that's what restraint is all about.
[SPEAKER_00]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about restraining greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not tolerate greed, aversion, delusion, not detain you, not indulge you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it isn't that, it's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's that's how you become aware of exactly what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your work.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by being aware of your work, then you can be diligent in regard to that work.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, doing it whenever it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a chore, but chore that can arise at any given time, or not arise for quite a while, but whenever it arises, it is done.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is absolutely no
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, I'll do it a bit later.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll do it tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't be bothered now.
[SPEAKER_01]: My meditation only starts at seven tonight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll deal with my sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you certainly cannot put a time schedule on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: One hour of dealing with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I can go back and sort of forget about it, because I've done my work for today.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes the whole day will be a chore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on some other days, you're going to have, like, weeks, months of no chores.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then arahant, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has done his duty, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: He finished all his chores.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has laid down the burden of duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he doesn't need to do anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, as a monk, that's pretty much the only thing you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, given the obviously practical necessities of patching your robes, walking Pindapad and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't take your whole day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the rest of the time, that is, that should be the monk's priority.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not tolerating greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarifying the work in regard to greed, aversion, delusion, and then being diligent in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if sometimes you wake up at two o'clock at night, and you wake up with a mind with, I don't know, affected by a hindrance or something, you have to do the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't go back to sleep until you do the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if sometimes, if you're sleepy at ten o'clock in the morning, and not as a hindrance, just as a genuine tiredness, because you got up at two o'clock at night, then you can go to sleep,
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't want to be tolerating greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's where the work is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And ultimately, of course, for anything sensed, like any sensed desire related, sensuality is the chief of the desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality, sexuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't tolerate that, you won't be tolerating anything inferior to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, if you free yourself from sexuality, you won't be attached to any other sensual experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, we go back to the importance of celibacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you also have to see the importance of... you've got to know that it's important to do that work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: By... that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands... he understands sensuality, the gratification of it, then the danger in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you understand the danger of slacking that particular work.
[SPEAKER_00]: You understand the danger of not doing that chore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: Any possible misfortune that can come your way is a result of you being in the domain where misfortunes can occur.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you place yourself in that domain by not disavowing, by not saying no to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, not freeing yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, people can say no, but still want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to stop wanting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the restraint is necessary, of course, because you can't, oh, I don't want it, but I'm engaging with it in my behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, your behavior perpetuates your wanting of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to stop the sensual behavior, you want to practice restraint, but that in itself is not enough either.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to use that, then, to actually discern and recognize that this is the extent of sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: No more, no less.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the extent of it, and I do not want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But until you discern the extent, you can't then decide, or rather you can't then develop your repulsion towards it, because you don't even know how big it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're like
[SPEAKER_00]: You say, you know, this sensuality usually then ends up being aimed to this particular thing, that particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But overall, your mind still finds the idea, the phenomenon, the most general phenomenon of sensuality, finds it pleasing, agreeable, welcomes it.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not engage in anything by body, by speech, not even necessarily in coarse thoughts, but you still have the attitude of, oh, this is... this is nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you wouldn't call nice something, if that something is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how nicely coated it is, you would say, oh, this is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he understands the gratification in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands the danger, and thus he knows the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't understand the gratification, well, you can't understand the danger, because the danger can apply only on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger as in, I don't want this.
[SPEAKER_01]: In terms of that mindfulness, you will slip from that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will slip from the composure that you understood or developed by going in to the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the only way to slip.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another thing that will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't slip by not making enough effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You slip by giving in to the opposing effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why all you need to do is just watch the gate, so to speak, the gatekeeper, as the Buddha would give those similes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to chase everything in or run after everything that goes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just stay at the gate, because you know that's where the problems arise, if they arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: The door, yeah, the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't give in to anything, just on that little level, no problems, nothing can actually arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: But giving in and then actually making that effort of giving in, yeah, that's how you fall for mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mindfulness becomes effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: When your mind is above sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as a reflection, you can... you can look at perception in the foreground and... Oh, that's... that's... that's the extent of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Perception in the foreground and feeling in the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was talking about in the essay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling, feeling and perceiving with perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are after pleasure in regard to agreeable perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means the feeling in the background motivates you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the important bit here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're just looking at perceptions, you'll be avoiding, you'll be denying, you'll be trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not uprooting anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in a way, that's how you realize, that's how you can discern the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you're restrained, you don't go and try to deny perceptions, in terms of you have a central thought arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: That has happened on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is if you give in to it, if you choose to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's that's obvious problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then the problem is also if you if you try to get rid of those thoughts as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must stop thinking, I must stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people do that very often, because it's actually unpleasant to have those thoughts enduring about in your mind, because you start to feel it more, the pressure of it, the pull, the pain, the dart, as the Buddha would call it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't feel it, you'll never realize the extent of gratification of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you shouldn't definitely not give in by body, speech or mind, but you should certainly not try to get rid of it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should be mindful in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And allow it to endure, just so that you can see the extent of the prospect of pleasure implied in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you do, then you see the extent of the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can say, I don't want it, on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it will work.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you say, I don't want it, to a too particular level, you're not applying that attitude of not wanting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is unwanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not applying it on a level of the nature of sensuality, which is far more general than the particular manifestation of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that generality is where you feel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sensuality, feeling in regards to sensuality, motivates your efforts, craving for that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about seeing, knowing feeling, seeing perception?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see that difference?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you know the feeling when you stop craving in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know the feeling when you psychologize or rationalize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you're just resorting to your perceptions again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you are... if you see perception or no perceptions correctly, then why would you give in to them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your feeling is still not free from craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you know the feeling as well... Well, you don't really know the perceptions until you know the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't know the feeling until you know the perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you won't be giving in to perception because... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because you're not giving in to perceptions because of perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: People give in to perceptions because of the craving in regard to feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they themselves create that magical connection from feeling into perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what I... this is what will satisfy.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's always on the domain of perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: And feeling always remains on the domain of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just recognizing that independence of each other in itself can significantly approve the craving from feeling towards my perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's no point.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing that they are just completely invisible to each other, so to speak, these two domains, you keep assuming this directionality, so to speak, of my dissatisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people say our sensuality can never satisfy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't, because it's applied here, and the problem was over here.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want that there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the problem here, I magically believe that me doing this here, gets rid of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just distracts you from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you forgetting about the problem of craving in regard to your feeling, you may... you develop a belief, which is why sensuality is an assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop a belief that, okay, that's... that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely magical connection between the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: We cannot... We try to manage our perceptions to get what feelings we want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's just... that is the way it has to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even when you start practicing restraint, it's a form of managing your perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't do it for its own sake.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're doing it for the sake of restraint, so that then you can develop the understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're just doing it for the sake of doing it, just management, then that's all it's going to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Management.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be restrained your whole life, but not understand anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still better than being non-restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not the dhamma, not the practice of it, certainly not the understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think you can interfere with feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you think you can go into that feeling and control it, manage it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you think you own the feelings, thus you feel entitled to... That's why the Buddha would say, well, which feeling do you own then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it a pleasant feeling, unpleasant or neutral?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you were truly the owner of
[SPEAKER_00]: The feeling domain, you would only feel pleasure all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact is that they come on their own and go their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, which one are you the master of?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what can you do with feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: What can you do with feelings?
[SPEAKER_00]: Allow them to endure, not act out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that will automatically result in mindfulness of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means being able to accept that initial pain of not acting out of feelings, wanting more, more of this, wanting less of that, more of this pleasure, less of that pain, wanting distraction in regard to this oppressing boredom, anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: All those things are felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's where the main problem is rooted in regard to those phenomena, which means you just have to learn how to endure them and not act out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But allow them to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only problem is you not being able to help yourself, but assume the ownership of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to undo that type of helplessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to get to understand them, so that then conceiving that you're their owner becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't really interfere.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't interfere with any of the aggregates, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even your intentions, which are usually the closest to the self point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only... the only things you can intend, are things that are given as options, as possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, even if you intend something, right here, right now, in this immediacy, it's because it was an option to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those options were already arisen, given on that peripheral level, on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even think of... you can't think anything from pure nothingness into being.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't create that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things are given on the peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, there are actual things present, as in the ones that you attend, on account of other things you don't attend to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, for example, I'm just having this in my mind now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like art.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I draw a picture that I've just created by myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't really create... Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You only created a particular arrangement of things that were all given beforehand, which means you only... you don't create any substance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You only affect the arrangement of the given substance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are equally on the level of arrangement, not in a substance, your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sense of self assumes this ultimate role that not just that it affects arrangement, it controls the substance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what sense of self assumes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it comes from the self-sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing that you can create.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely nothing that you can create.
[SPEAKER_00]: From that fundamental point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything you can do... Well, anything that you can do means it's anything that you can intend and attend.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything you can intend and attend, has had to be given beforehand, as an option, to intend it or attend it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every, like, myriad of implications, as options, possibilities, things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're kind of bound with the purpose, bound with the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all of that comes from the background, over which you actually have no control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the direction that you cannot go under and kind of hold it up as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to do so is to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the Buddha doesn't create the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the thing as most universal, most profound, is the dhamma itself, the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't create this.
[SPEAKER_00]: No Buddha created this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just find it like an old path that's been overgrown in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing you can possibly create.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one has the understanding of dhamma, the vision of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, having that as your center, not as your center,
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're composed in the in the balance of the right principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when sometimes they will insist and ask the Buddha on the... oh, what's the... what happens... what happens for an ārahant?
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens when there is no self?
[SPEAKER_00]: And things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he would either just dismiss the questions on self and not-self, if they're formulated wrongly, or the
[SPEAKER_00]: The most direct answer he would give to that would be quite indirect.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be the description of what teaches him upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what's left.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: With ignorance, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without ignorance, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the experience is without ignorance, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the arahant's balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in a way, even Putujana is in a balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, even Putujana, with all his ignorance, can't do anything different to the nature of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only thing different there is his appropriation of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The gratuitous appropriation, that's not the aggregates, that's just an attitude in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely baseless attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he said Avijay is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no first point when he was, oh, on account of this Avijay came.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's just there, but it shouldn't be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you understand that it cannot be there, that's where it disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: What comes to mind is that the middle way, in the way of right composure, balance, that is, it's not moderation, the way of moderation, the dhamma is not... No, not necessarily, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when people act out of the view of moderation,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's their self-view that decides what's moderate, based on things that they've experienced, which means moderation, it's a very relative thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's moderate for somebody, won't be moderating for somebody else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eventually, it won't be even moderating for you enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the moderation is only in regard to your previous behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if your behavior was already behavior moderation, then the new moderation is going to be even more moderate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what happened to giants, when they were just going further and further and further in saying those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also when they asked the Buddha... Well, the Buddha asked the man...
[SPEAKER_00]: The man praised the Buddha, and then he asked, what do you think... Why do you think that all these disciples have respect for me?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the man said, ah, because Master Gautama praises eating little and...
[SPEAKER_00]: He eats little and he praises eating little.
[SPEAKER_00]: He lives rough, he plays living rough, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, well, if they were true, means that I have...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes I eat a bowl full, full to the brim.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes I have a second one, full to the brim.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I have disciples that, at the same time, would live on a... on house rice, just a handful every two or three days would get.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all they would eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were to respect me on account of eating little, they wouldn't, because they eat less than me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it goes on about any kind of ascetic practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes I stay in king's palaces, while I have disciples living under a root of tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were to respect me on account of that, they wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do they respect me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I taught suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I taught pratīcṭhāna, upādāna, and he lists all these different ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: I taught jhānas, all these different ways of practice towards understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, like, that's why they respect me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of that moderation or asceticism, if it's taken further, sometimes helpful for somebody, sometimes it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the criteria is not what I think helpful is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The criteria is that vision of dhamma that you open up with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you said the right composure, the right view, the
[SPEAKER_00]: The right understanding, that's the criteria for those people, which then means they will know if increasing asceticism results in unwholesome, to increase and wholesome to decrease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, if they realize, okay, so asceticism doesn't work for this set of aggregates at this set of time, so they may be
[SPEAKER_00]: If you eat more and rest a bit more, but practice better, that doesn't mean that you're always gonna stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they don't decide.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a response to wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't decide before?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't decide, well, I'm this type or this is what works for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Today that might work for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tomorrow you might have to go under a root of a tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said, let those who want.
[SPEAKER_00]: To eat out of, like, live under root of tree, wear hemp robes and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let those who don't want, not do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That, of course, doesn't mean the ones who doesn't want to do it, they'll go back and live in the city surrounded with unrestrained people and engage in spirituality.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just means how moderate you become.
[SPEAKER_00]: How, sort of, committed to the idea of moderation, which, again, two bowls of food once a day, it's not necessarily much.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite moderate amount.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... for somebody who eats only one handful a day, well, that's just pure indulgence, if he were to just look at it from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: The middle way, not giving in to... Middle way means, basically, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, no, no, no...
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_00]: Living at the root of a tree is extreme for somebody.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, middle way means, eh... means, eh... not giving in to the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not indulging it, not ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Middle way means dead balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Middle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the balance is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's free from unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's got nothing to do with the content, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, there is the obvious content of the Eight Precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: They must stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: But any other content, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, people can wear hemp robes and live under a root of tree and be extremely misguided and conceited and vain.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, like, for goodness sake, even... what's his name?
[SPEAKER_00]: Devadatta, the one who tried to kill the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was, like, full-on ascetic.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, people were inspired by him.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he went to the Buddha... that was actually the sutra that I mentioned.
[SPEAKER_00]: He went to the Buddha and demanded that all these ascetic practices be made compulsory for all the monks, because it's so inspirational, it's so great.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, no, don't ask me that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't ask the Tathāgata that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, let those who want to do those practices, do those practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, again, that doesn't mean, okay, so I can live a lax and luxurious life.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to keep the perspective on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even the ones who don't do the ascetic practices are still quite an ascetic from a lay unrestrained point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you can't expect to eat five times a day, engage in distractions, just think about your work projects and fantasies and whatnot, and think, oh, well, I'm a, you know, ascetic renunciate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I don't have to live under a rooted tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but you also have... you also don't have to engage with unwholesome either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like somebody can wear silk robes and not care about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody can wear hemp robes and actually be quite unwholesome about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean there's no value in trying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, it's not a fixed thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not set in stone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Today you might not mind about silk robes, but tomorrow you might start to be quite attached to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Equally, tomorrow, today you might mind the hemp robes, be very conceited about it, but tomorrow you might see that conceit, and then abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why you can't just prescribe everybody to do that all the time, because there will be an external reference point, which, if people don't see, it's meaningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you just emulate things without understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even worse, you're not even aware that you're just emulating.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think, oh, so if I do this prescription, this method, this set of observances, always without having to think about anything, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will result in arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the recognition of that balance, the mindful composure, that can result in knowledge and vision.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's even the right ordination in the right lineage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right monastic lineage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That solves all the problems.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: External reference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Monk's certificate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Got that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Monk's certificate, your tradition, your upajāya, your ācārya.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all this, like, like, institutional reputation and whatnot.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's, that's a lay, lay setup.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have an institution, means there is no, like, again, you can have people practicing within the institution.
[SPEAKER_00]: But institution itself, it's actually a counterbalance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's based on the external projection of value, importance, recognition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means there's no individual responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's the tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You choose to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you could choose to not do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you're gonna feel that then, weight of your choice, every single day.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not if you just submit and subscribe to tradition, whatever that tradition might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that does the work for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why people like that, and we met a few, would get very, very kind of anxiously upset and defensive, if somebody just not even dismisses their tradition, just doesn't acknowledge it sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because their whole mode of being is projected on the external observances and form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is what monks are all about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's an external reference point that as such cannot stand in place for the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the dhamma, the right view, is to be developed and known individually by those who are wise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's the same principle that's developed by different people, different sotāpannas, different arahants and so on, but it doesn't mean that they will all act the same, like robotic sort of clones or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're different, different aggregates, different individuals.
[SPEAKER_00]: What they all have in common is freedom from greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how will that manifest in their behavior?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you cannot possibly write a prescription for that in some sort of conformity or behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: As much as visually pleasing is, that is for some people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody walking in line.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone's saying once, it's like trying to make everyone wear the same size shorts or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, okay, yes, yeah, in a way, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't work, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's why, that's why, like, again, you know, there's more than enough rules, precepts, they've been formed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within that, the only reason, if you were going for more, it's because you are, you are sort of misdirecting your practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because why would you need more conformity rules, for example, in the traditions and... Like, seriously, when you don't
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you don't wear your lower robe like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not our tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you fold it counterclockwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: I fold it with this side, you fold it that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that's against our tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why would you even need that kind of observance to the point of anxiously kind of getting upset with all the other rules that the Buddha formed, when he himself said nobody should be forming rules after I pass away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you can say, oh, there's no rules, but yeah, you see how lightly they were taken then, or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognize that already the plenty of basis, or plenty of rules for the basis, to develop basis of virtue and so on, and then you have to start taking responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: If not, you can spend hundred years in robes, and be an equal for two jhāna, that's not free from even like the low three fetters, let alone sensuality and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you never took responsibility for the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was projected out on the method, on the teacher, on the tradition, on the institution, whatever, but not on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... when there is ignorance or confusion about the structure of reality,
[SPEAKER_01]: That is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because we...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can say that in an impersonal manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing is, obviously, the notion of what structure is, that's already part of the confusion in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the confusion in regard to the structure of reality means freeing the
[SPEAKER_00]: It means freeing the structure of reality from craving, from greed, aversion, delusion, not from laying it all out and figuring it out, because that would require an external point of view to the structure, which means then it's not a structure, if you can step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, getting back to foreground, background, in regards to super-nimitta, so the attractive, sign of attractiveness,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, attract... the sign of attractment is also something that's in the background, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I see a person, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: The... whether it's subha or then asubha, it's in regard to what's being perceived in the foreground, through the six senses, either the sight, sound, smell, taste, touch or thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's because that subha is in that background, which is usually also where... well, not usually, which is where people's feelings as well are.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you kind of end up assuming the craving for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: The attraction of the background, the pleasant feeling of the background, you end up identifying it with what you're perceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you end up wanting it, aiming at it, acting towards it, consuming it and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, becoming aware of the sub-animity means becoming aware of the phenomenon of beautiful, of attractive, of attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, that doesn't mean that that becomes your foreground or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's still in regard to the foreground of the sense experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, by discerning the sub-animity, for example, you can then look further, in the further background to it, which is the sub-animity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why every... any beautiful, any attractive, it's on the basis of unattractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the basis of ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just where it arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to that which is equally same, perceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same object you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when attraction is the nimitta, as in the attraction is the unseen background, that's what determines your attraction towards that object.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you look beyond that background and see even further,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's much more unattractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fundamentally unattractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it weren't so, you wouldn't be able to free yourself from the attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But attraction is always secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because people never question it, always indulge it, or more often than not, they indulge it, they give into it, you never get to see what's beyond the attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just attraction, you're out chasing the object that you're attracted to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you start seeing the attraction, you're gonna start seeing... Well, you start seeing the attraction when you stop, by default, chasing the objects of your attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will just force you to be with your attraction, which will then reveal that, oh, well, there is more to be seen in regard to this attraction, while the same objects are present in the foreground, as a thought or sight and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you get to see the unattractive behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure of attraction, like the unpleasantness of that central pull.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say there's passion, and then seeing that passion can reveal the more fundamental... Yeah, yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what means it's always the first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, you need to start seeing the attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start to start seeing the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to start seeing things that you're supposed to overcome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just deny them, or not even look in that direction, or expect to be doing something here, and they're going to disappear from over there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you realize there cannot be a sub... there cannot be sub-nimitta without the foundations of a sub-nimitta.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's hot.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just cannot be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any subha-nimitta, if you discern long enough, you realize, ah, whenever there is... You can have a subha that's a subha, or you can have a subha that's less a subha, which is how it's perceived to be from the sensuality point of view, which is subha then.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sign of beauty, it's basically the sign of less ugly, but still pertaining to the nature of ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like beautiful and ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ugly and less ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Disgusting and slightly less disgusting, but equally disgusting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, a spoonful of excrement is less disgusting than a bucketful, if you have to, you know, engage with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's actually equally disgusting.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people forget that great... that greater context of sharing the nature of disgusting, and then, oh no, this is actually quite agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: The less disgusting becomes desirable, becomes your sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's equally disgusting, in terms of pertaining to the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just less disgusting in its content, but the nature is equally disgusting.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can only see that once, first, by accepting the sublimity for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can only accept it by stop acting out of it, stop indulging it, stop being non-restrained and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when you accept it, then you get to see it, and then you can see further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can see that there is a subha-nimitta and a subha-nimitta, or there can be subha-nimitta, which means that's a subha-nimitta there as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: A subha can be present through subha and a subha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it doesn't matter if it's subha or a subha, a subha is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if it's unattractive, disgusting, or a little bit less unattractive and a little bit less disgusting, the disgust is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The foreground is diversified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the foreground diversifies, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The background is more... unifies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The background is that... it's where the nature of that... it's that which determines the diversity.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a reference point for diversity, a reference point for a change, a reference point for time-lapsing.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that, it's pertaining to the foreground.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, something needs to remain unchanged while change occurs, so that you can see that there is a change.
[SPEAKER_00]: If everything is changing all the time, constantly, well, there is no change at all, because you can't tell that everything is changing, because everything is changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or things can change at different rate, perhaps, and then the thing that changes at a lesser rate,
[SPEAKER_00]: It can become a reference point for a thing that changes at a quicker rate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that might be too abstract for some people to ponder on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can, you can, you can, you can practice that on the level of feelings and moods, like the general feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you can have a general, a general feeling present of you being okay or you being not okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: While they're particular,
[SPEAKER_00]: More diversified feelings occurring on a daily basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: But overall, you're okay, you're meeting in all sorts of disagreeable feelings on an individual level, like, oh, this is annoying, this is disappointing and stuff, but none of that to the point of changing your general feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when that general feeling changes, and it will, then even the other things that you're encountering that are agreeable,
[SPEAKER_00]: will not necessarily make you happy or bring you back into the good mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could see there, like, it becomes almost like a reference point, the general feeling to the particular feelings that you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reference point that determines whether you're happy or not, really, whether you're suffering or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when people are in a good mood and they can take on the world, because nothing can make them suffer, because this mood is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they fail to see that that mood has arisen on its own, which means, as such, it will have to go on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means then, if you established your whole well-being upon that mood, when that mood goes, you're going to be compromised, seriously compromised.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the more you establish the mind on the background... Well, you want to be starting to discern peripheral in regard to the peripheral moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not always, like, from that point of view,
[SPEAKER_00]: The new peripheral, in regard to general moods, would be that, almost like equanimity, would be the sign of the nimitta, in regard to the general moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you just see this feeling comes and goes, this feeling comes and goes, this feeling comes and goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would be in common to these feelings?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not coming and going.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just sort of being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Phenomenon that's not being felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like nibbāna is the ultimate dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in the most general fundamental dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still a dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nothing transcendental in a sense of outside of this experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still a dhamma, but a dhamma that's free from greed, aversion, delusion, free from being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: That now has became pretty much the mode of your existence here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind has been developed to such an apex that is just unshakable from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's irreversible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the balance, the balance, the perfected balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it's just the notion of imbalance disappears, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say, if you look at the phenomenon of things, some things in general, things, experience, whatever is in front of you, the most general experience, and then what is
[SPEAKER_01]: Ultimately speaking, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ultimate negative, the nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can go even further.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say whatever is the foreground.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever, anything that arises,
[SPEAKER_00]: What do all those things have in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: That they're present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, then, the ultimate sign to that is absence.
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility of absence.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's nothing other than death.
[SPEAKER_00]: The notion of death that people have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why the Buddha did say, the one who practices mindfulness of death, it's like the quickest way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nibbāna, it's almost like dying without actually dying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Extinguishing your being, extinguishing your sense of self, extinguishing your likes, your affections, your attractions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what people are terrified from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even back in the day, when the Buddha would lay it out for them, and they would get shocked, panic, fall down on the ground in despair, pulling their hair, shouting that, well, if we practice that, that will kill me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's exactly what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: For Putujana,
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma is if they go through the notion of their own death without dying, without doing anything on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why many practitioners turn away from it and jump onto the rituals, rules, traditions, whatever else, so they don't take responsibility, because if they do, it becomes apparent that it's on you and means if you keep doing it, you will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what even Ajahn Chah said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Our practice of dhamma is like die, you should die.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you practice dhamma, you will die before you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just a poetic expression.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or like, you know, edgy inspiration.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people... Those people understood what nibbāna was.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the thing, when the Buddha would teach them.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha would say what his teaching is, they would understand what he was talking for nibbāna to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they would freak out.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... And again, it's nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing transcendental in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: People are not in nibbāna is because they don't value the nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't value the absence of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't value the imperturbable, not being felt, unshakable states.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't value that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how do you know that they don't value?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, just have somebody, yourself, if you have doubts, lock yourself in a room, don't have any distraction, don't do anything for a whole day, just one day, and see.
[SPEAKER_00]: How close to the freaking out you're going to get with boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: First boredom, then it's going to turn into dread and anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that peaceful feeling of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Pratyujana experienced it as a dread and anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not me, not my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: I better distract myself from this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he were to prepare himself to not be afraid of that feeling, that's that peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the Buddha would say that the neutral feeling, the sublime neutral feeling, the refined neutral feeling,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, it's valued by the wise.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pleasant when it's known, and unpleasant when it isn't known.
[SPEAKER_01]: Valuing it, knowing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, they can value it because they know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, no, this is actually the true peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Putujana doesn't have peace, doesn't have nibbāna, not because his eyes are covered by the metaphysical veil of māyā and illusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's because he just doesn't value it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't recognize it first, then he doesn't value it, even if he were to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even further, he's actively afraid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's terrified of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he's not in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to stop being afraid of your own death, for example, and you're already closer to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's why people are afraid of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because they know what death is, but because death is just this vague direction of absence of all of this, that I hold dear.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't be afraid of death, because you don't... you can't even see the death coming.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always in the direction external to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always from the opposing direction from where you look.
[SPEAKER_00]: You being afraid of death, it's only possible because you see a relationship, you see a reference to absence and denial of everything that you hold dear in your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, because you're attached to life, you fear the absence of life, which is what death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove the attachment to life, the kind of attitude of holding it dear and delighting in it, why would you be afraid if the whole thing goes?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fear will become inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why arahant is ultimately beyond death, beyond that fear of that relationship of absence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because puthujjana can't even conceive death.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think death, you think in positive terms again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for many people, just a mere change, it's almost on the level of freaking out as if they would when they experience death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let alone if things actually do start.
[SPEAKER_00]: Going into the absent mode, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Losing your senses and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that is the ultimate nimitta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you can use those perceptions to establish your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Establish your mind from the perception of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Going beyond perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, it would go.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the sign?
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that will be the ultimate non-indicative, non-appropriating consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in presence that doesn't appropriate any presence.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will be your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like when consciousness doesn't indicate any ownership, any sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nor the matter finds any footing in that experience anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just left.
[SPEAKER_00]: In seen, there will be the seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: In heard, just the heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on for all the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.